We're going to move a little bit into the user-facing space now, with ISPF and TSO.
現在我們來看看使用者介面，包含 ISPF 和 TSO。
ISPF is the Interactive System Productivity Facility, and TSO is the time-sharing option.
ISPF 是 Interactive System Productivity Facility，TSO 是 time-sharing option。
These are two separate products, both of which run on the mainframe in the ZOS operating system.
這兩者是獨立產品，都在主機的 z/OS 作業系統上執行。
And a short detour here about acronyms.
這裡稍微說明一下縮寫。
We just talked about ISPF, and I told you that it stands for the Interactive System Productivity Facility.
剛剛提到 ISPF，我說它代表 Interactive System Productivity Facility。
Now, I had to look that up, because I have literally never called it the Interactive System Productivity Facility.
老實說我查過，因為我從沒真的叫過它完整名稱。
It's always just been ISPF, and you'll probably never hear anybody say time-sharing option either, it's just TSO.
它總是叫 ISPF，你也幾乎不會聽到有人說 time-sharing option， 都是叫 TSO。
What I'm getting at here is that you shouldn't worry about memorizing what things stand for,
我的意思是你不用刻意背縮寫代表什麼，
unless they help you remember it, like peachid.
除非它能幫助你記憶，例如 peachid。
The P in the front of peachid reminds me of the physical channel path identifier.
peachid 前面的 P 讓我聯想到物理通道路徑識別碼。
But you've probably noticed that we go through a lot of acronyms here, and I just don't need to stress about memorizing things.
你可能已經注意到我們使用了很多縮寫，但我不需要強迫自己記住它們。
What's important is what they are.
重要的是它們代表什麼。
And ISPF is a full-screen, menu-driven interface which lets you access ZOS tools and utilities.
ISPF 是一個全屏幕、選單導向的介面，讓你能使用 z/OS 工具與實用程式。
So, instead of memorizing commands and parameters, you can just navigate to a panel built specifically for the task you want to do,
因此，你不用記憶指令和參數，只要導航到專為你要執行的任務設計的面板，
and enter the options you want.
然後輸入你想要的選項。
TSO kind of runs behind ISPF, supporting it, and is typically used for one-word or one-line commands.
TSO 在 ISPF 背後運行，提供支援，通常用於單字或單行指令。
So, for most tasks, you've got the option of either doing it through TSO or ISPF.
所以，大部分任務你可以選擇用 TSO 或 ISPF 來完成。
When you first connect to a mainframe using a terminal emulator, you're greeted by a TSO logon screen.
當你第一次使用終端模擬器連接主機時，會看到 TSO 登入畫面。
Top of the screen, you may notice this little slash E at the end of TSO, and you're wondering what that is.
畫面上方，你可能會注意到 TSO 末端有個小斜線 E，不禁好奇那是什麼。
That means it's TSO Extensions, which has a few improvements over the original TSO.
那代表是 TSO Extensions，具有比原始 TSO 更多的改進功能。
But, again, most people just call it TSO.
但大多數人還是稱它為 TSO。
You log into TSO with a username and a password.
您需使用使用者名稱和密碼登入 TSO。
So, we need to move our cursor over to the User ID field and put in our User ID,
請將游標移至 User ID 欄位，並輸入您的使用者 ID，
and then there's a password field right over here. Do the same thing with the password.
然後在密碼欄位輸入密碼。
Many of these fields will be filled out with the default values when you get there,
許多欄位預設會自動帶入預設值，
and if they are, you're probably okay just to leave them like that.
如果有預設值，通常可以直接保留不變。
A quick word about navigating to fields.
快速講一下如何移動欄位。
The easiest way to move from field to field is by hitting the Tab key,
最簡單的方式是按 Tab 鍵在欄位間切換，
and you can go the other direction by hitting Shift-Tab.
按 Shift+Tab 則可往回切換。
If you try to use your mouse to select the fields you want to type in,
如果您試著用滑鼠選取想輸入的欄位，
it's real easy to click in the wrong spot, and then you'll wind up putting text where you didn't mean to.
很容易點錯地方，結果文字會出現在不該出現的地方。
So, for a lot of what we're going to be doing, just use your keyboard.
所以，接下來大部分時間請用鍵盤操作。
So, now you've got your User ID and your password in there,
現在你已經輸入了 User ID 和密碼，
and below that we've got this Procedure field.
在下面我們看到這個 Procedure 欄位。
This is the procedure that kicks off when you start your TSO session.
這是啟動 TSO 工作階段時執行的程序。
This is usually set up for you by someone who knows what they're doing,
通常會由有經驗的人幫你設定，
so it's best not to change it unless you really need to or someone tells you to.
所以除非必要或有人指示，最好不要更改。
And even then, make sure you make a note of what it said before in case you need to change it back.
即使要改，也要先記下原本的內容，方便還原。
The account number is used to track system usage,
帳號用來追蹤系統使用情況，
and the Size field determines the amount of memory that your TSO session gets.
Size 欄位決定你的 TSO 工作階段可用的記憶體大小。
Perform is there in case you want to associate your TSO session
Perform 是用來將您的 TSO 工作階段關聯到一組效能特性，這對 WLM 很有幫助。
with a set of performance characteristics, which can be helpful for WLM.
這樣可以讓 WLM 更好地管理資源。
And then there's Command.
還有 Command。
This tells TSO what you want it to do once you're logged in.
這告訴 TSO 登入後要執行什麼動作。
You may be prompted to change your password, or you may just feel like changing your password.
系統可能會要求您更改密碼，或者您也可以主動更改密碼。
To do that, enter your current password in the Password field
要執行此操作，請在 Password 欄位輸入目前密碼。
and put your new password over in the New Password field.
然後在 New Password 欄位輸入新密碼。
You will then be prompted to enter the same password again,
接著系統會要求您再次輸入同樣的密碼，
just to make sure you typed out what you meant to type.
以確保您輸入的密碼正確無誤。
The Group Identification field can be used to log into another group
Group Identification 欄位可用於登入其它群組。
and access a different set of resources.
並存取不同的資源集。
If that's done, it'll typically be done by the Security Administrator.
如果要執行這項操作，通常會由安全管理員負責。
Then down here, we've got four options.
接著在這邊，我們有四個選項。
To select any one of these options, place an S to select it in the space before it.
要選擇其中一個選項，請在其前方的空格中輸入 S。
So if you put an S before NoMail, TSO will suppress the messages intended for you,
所以如果你在 NoMail 前輸入 S，TSO 將會抑制傳給你的訊息，
specifically during the logon process.
特別是在登入過程中。
Put an S in front of No Notice,
在 No Notice 前輸入 S，
and that says you don't want to see any of the messages intended for all users.
這表示你不想看到傳給所有使用者的訊息。
Next, if you ever accidentally close your terminal window,
接著，如果你不小心關閉了終端機視窗，
there's a chance it'll notice this and close up your session safely.
系統有機會察覺到這點，並安全地關閉你的工作階段。
But if, for whatever reason, you're trying to log in,
但是如果你因為某些原因嘗試登入，
and it's telling you your session is already in use,
系統告訴你你的工作階段已在使用中，
you can select this and it will reconnect you to that previously running session.
你可以選擇這個選項，它會重新連接到先前的工作階段。
And then there's OID card.
接著是OID card。
You can use this to enter data using your Operator Identification card,
你可以用它來輸入資料，前提是你有Operator Identification card。
if you have one of those.
如果你有的話。
All right, now we're in ISPF.
好了，我們現在進入ISPF介面。
Let's see what we got.
來看看有什麼功能。
Up top, we've got the Action Bar.
頂部是Action Bar。
This works just like a menu in anything else you've ever used.
它的功能就像你用過的任何選單一樣。
And then there's a Command Line.
還有一個命令列。
That lets you type out any commands that you know.
它讓你輸入所有你知道的指令。
This may also be located at the bottom of the screen instead of the top.
它也可能位於畫面底部，而非頂端。
Some people like it down there, and they'll set it up that way.
有些人喜歡把它放在底部，且會這樣設定。
Next, there's this big listing of panel options.
接著，是這一大串的面板選項。
And these show you all the panels that you can go to in ISPF.
這些會顯示你在 ISPF 可以進入的所有面板。
So if you want to go to Dialogue Test, for example,
所以舉例來說，如果你想進入 Dialogue Test，
you would put a 7 on the Command Line and then hit Enter,
你會在命令列輸入 7，然後按 Enter，
because 7 is the number on the panel options for Dialogue Test.
因為 7 是面板選項中 Dialogue Test 的編號。
At the bottom, there's a listing of function keys.
底部會列出功能鍵。
These remind you of what you can do using the function or F keys on your keyboard.
這些提醒您可以使用鍵盤上的功能鍵或F鍵執行的操作。
For example, F7 goes backward and F8 goes forward when you're working on a program or a file
例如，當您處理大於螢幕顯示的程式或檔案時，F7會向後，F8會向前。
that's bigger than your screen will fit.
超出螢幕可顯示範圍的部分。
Now, if you're looking down at your keyboard and wondering,
現在，如果您低頭看著鍵盤並想知道，
what are these function F keys all about?
這些功能F鍵到底是什麼？
They're usually in the row above where your numbers are.
它們通常位於數字鍵的上方一排。
And if you don't have that row or they look a little bit different,
如果您沒有這一排或者它們看起來有點不同，
you might have to use like a modifier key or remap some of these keys.
您可能需要使用修飾鍵或重新對這些鍵進行映射。
But that's something you can explore during the labs.
但這部分您可以在實驗課中嘗試探索。
We also have this dynamic status area.
我們也有這個動態狀態區域。
This area can change.
這個區域可以變動。
That's why it's called the dynamic status area.
這就是為什麼它被稱為動態狀態區。
And it's an area set aside in the panel configuration,
這是面板設定中專門保留的區域，
and it's controlled by an ISPF variable.
並由 ISPF 變數控制。
It's almost always used just to provide you with additional helpful information.
它幾乎總是用來提供額外的有用資訊。
So we're all done now.
所以我們現在全部完成了。
How do we disconnect?
我們要怎麼斷線？
There's a couple of ways I'm going to show you too.
我也會示範你幾種方法。
You can enter X on the Command Line or you can press F12, the Cancel key.
你可以在命令列輸入 X，或按 F12 取消鍵。
This will end ISPF and put you back to a TSO Command Line,
這會結束 ISPF，並回到 TSO 命令列，
because TSO is still running.
因為 TSO 還在執行。
It's not the same thing as ISPF.
這跟 ISPF 不一樣。
And if you want to go back into ISPF, just enter the Command ISPF and hit Enter.
如果想回到 ISPF，只要輸入指令 ISPF 並按 Enter。
To terminate TSO, enter the Command Log Off and hit Enter.
若要終止 TSO，輸入指令 Log Off 並按 Enter。
And TSO will cleanly close down and disconnect you.
TSO 會乾淨地關閉並斷線。
But don't worry, we'll be back.
別擔心，我們會回來的。